<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A notable and learned sermon or homilie, made vpon saint Andrewes daye last past 1556 in the Cathedral curche of S. Paule in London, by Mayster Ihon Harpesfeild doctour of diuinitie and canon residenciary of the sayd churche, set furthe by the bishop of London.</title>
            <author>Harpsfield, John, 1516-1578.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1536</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 27 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 21 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A02663</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 12795</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S112490</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99847739</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99847739</idno>
            <idno type="VID">12799</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A02663)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 12799)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 464:05)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A notable and learned sermon or homilie, made vpon saint Andrewes daye last past 1556 in the Cathedral curche of S. Paule in London, by Mayster Ihon Harpesfeild doctour of diuinitie and canon residenciary of the sayd churche, set furthe by the bishop of London.</title>
                  <author>Harpsfield, John, 1516-1578.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[40] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>By Robert Caly, within the precinct of the late dessolued house of the graye freers, nowe conuerted to an hospitall, called Christes Hospitall],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[Imprynted at London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>Vltimo Decembris 1556.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Printer's name from colophon.</note>
                  <note>At foot of title page: Cum priuilegio ad imprimendum solum.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Bodleian Library.</note>
                  <note>Signatures: A-B C⁴(-C4).</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Sermons, English --  16th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2008-05</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2008-10</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-07</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-07</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:12799:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:12799:1"/>
            <p>¶A notable and learned Sermon or Homilie, made vpon ſaint An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drewes daye laſt paſt 1556. in the Cathedral churche of S. Paule in London, by Mayſter Ihon Harpeſfeild doctour of duinitie and Canon reſidenciary of the ſayd churche, Set furth by the biſhop of London.</p>
            <p>Vltimo Decembris, 1556.</p>
            <p>
               <floatingText xml:lang="lat">
                  <body>
                     <div type="license">
                        <p>¶ Cum priuilegio ad impri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mendum ſolum.</p>
                     </div>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
            </p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:12799:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:12799:2"/>
            <head>Conſtituite diem ſolennem in condenſis, vſo<expan>
                  <am>
                     <g ref="char:abque"/>
                  </am>
                  <ex>que</ex>
               </expan> ad cornu altaris.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">H</seg>Onorable, wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shipfull, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uout chriſtia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience, the holy prophet Dauid, in his hundreth and xvii pſalme (whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce the wordes of my theme are taken out) dothe in treate of foure pointes moſte mete to bee duety co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſidered, and effectually of vs all practiced at this preſe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t. Fyrſt he declareth that himſelfe had been in extreme perill and daunger of life, and in great af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fliction &amp; tribulation of mynde. Secondely, he acknowledgeth that God of his infinite mercye and goodnes did delmer him.
<pb facs="tcp:12799:3"/>Thirdelye that he doeth eſteme thoſe daungers and vexacions as a ſcourge for ſynne. Fourth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lye and laſte he geueth thankes vnto GOD his deliuerer, and exhorteth al other to do the like.</p>
            <p>Concerning the perill he was in, he ſayth: <hi>Circundantes circun dederunt me ſicutapes.</hi> My ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies compaſſed me round about as thicke as it had ben a ſwarm of Bees. And againe within a while after. <hi>Impulſus euerſus ſum ut caderem,</hi> I was thruſte at ſo ſore, that I was lyke to be ouer-throwne: and after that he cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth him ſelfe, <hi>lapide<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> quem repro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bauerunt ędifica<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tes.</hi> A ſton which the builders did refuſe and caſt awaye: meaning in thoſe .iii. pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, the perſecution whiche he ſuſteyned at the handes of wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked
<pb facs="tcp:12799:3"/>Saul, who (as it is written in the fyrſt booke of the kinges) ſometime threwe a darte at Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uid: ſometyme ſent men ſodenlye Dauids houſe, to take him in his beed and bringe him vnto him, that he might be ſlain: ſom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>time perſecuted him with an ope<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> armye. Concerning the ſeconde pointe, whiche is how Dauid in the forſaied Pſalme dothe con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſe and acknowledge that god of his mere goodnes miraculouſ lye protected and deliuered hym, it is there written. <hi>Dominus ſuſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepit me,</hi> God was my help. <hi>For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titudo &amp; laus mea dominus, &amp; fac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus eſt mihi in ſalutem,</hi> God is my ſtrength &amp; my reioyſing, and is become my ſaluatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. <hi>Dextera do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mini fecit uirtutem, dextera domi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ni exaltauit me, dextera domine fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cit
<pb facs="tcp:12799:4"/>virtutem.</hi> The ryght hande of God hathe done myghtelye, the right hande of God hath exalted me, the right hande of God hath done myghtely. Concerning the thirde pointe, whiche is that the prophet Dauid cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>teth his trou bles and perſecutions as a cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtiſement for ſinne, he ſayth. <hi>Caſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tigans caſtigauit me dominus.</hi> God hathe chaſtened &amp; corrected me. The laſte and fourthe pointe is thankes geuing &amp; prouoking all other to the like. This point is to be fou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d in many places of the Pſalme, but moſt notably in the wordes of my theme when he ſaieth: <hi>Conſtituite diem ſolennem in condenſis vſo<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> ad cornu altaris.</hi> Appoint you to kepe a ſolempne feaſte, in great frequencies or multitudes, &amp; co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>courſe of people
<pb facs="tcp:12799:4"/>euen reachinge to the corners of the alter. It was commaunded in the old lawe that at ſolempne feaſtes the people ſhould bringe Oxen, Calues, lambes, or Goa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes, to be offred vp vpon the aul<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ter in ſacrifice, and that the preiſt ſhoulde ſprynkell of the bloude vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the corners of the aultar: &amp; he nowe exhorteth them ſo to do, in geuynge thankes to God, for that he had deliuered him out of the handes of Saul: and he mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth them to kepe a newe ſolem<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>netie for this purpoſe, beſides the accuſtomed feaſtes cominau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded in the lawe. Accordynge to this example geuen vs by kynge Dauid, it is our parte to vſe our ſelfes this preſent daye. Firſt to remember what miſerable and parilous caſe we were in of late
<pb facs="tcp:12799:5"/>yeres. Nexte to conſider howe God by his myghtye hande, and thoroughe hys infinite mercye hathe deliuered vs. Thirdlye to perſwade oure ſelues, that wee worthely ſuffered thoſe miſeries for oure ſynnes. Fourthlye to be thankefull, and induce other to tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>kes geuing for our deliuery. Whiche that ye may the rather do, I intende by Goddes grace and your patience, to ſtande vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the twoo fyrſte pointes, and to ſet forth the excedinge greate benefite of oure reconciliation to the vnitie of the catholike chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che, and the horrible miſeries which we were in, in the tyme of ſchiſme and diuiſion, &amp; then no more, but touche the other two partes, and ſo committe you to God. And that the thinges to be
<pb facs="tcp:12799:5"/>vttered at this preſente by me, may be to Gods honour, to your edification and comforte, I de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſyre you fyrſte to helpe me with your prayers.</p>
            <p>The prayers.</p>
            <p>I Fynde in holye ſcripture that there wer two comen weales, inſtituted, ordei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, and appoynted by God him ſelfe. The one emonge the chyl<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren of Iſraell, the other emong the chriſtians. The co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mon weale of the Iſraelites or Iewes, was in tyme before the comminaltie of chriſtendome. But this in wor thines is farre before it. For the thinges belo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ging to that eſtate, were figures, types, and ſhado<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wes of thynges belonginge too chriſtianitie. The children of Iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rael were vnder cruel Pharao, in
<pb facs="tcp:12799:6"/>great captiuitie &amp; thraldom, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>til ſuch time as god of his good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes called them outs of Egypte, and drowned their enemyes in the redde Sea: lykewiſe is all mankinde thrall to the ſpiritual Pharao, that is the deuil, before they comme to paſſe thoroughe baptiſme, whiche becauſe it ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth his force and ſtrength of the bloud of our ſauiour, and is mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtred in water, maye well be lykened to the read Sea, and in it all power of the deuill is quite ouer whelmed and deſtroyed. The chyldren of Iſraell hauing paſſed the read Sea, were not furth w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> directly conueied to the lande of promiſe: but were faine to traueill in the baren &amp; vnplea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſaunt wyldernes, a longe ſpace, there abiding muche trouble and
<pb facs="tcp:12799:6"/>vexation. Euen ſo chriſten peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple after their Baptiſme are left in this vale of miſerie, here to en<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dure many ſharp &amp; perilous ſtor<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>mes, and are not immediatly fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the Font, had vp to the lande of the liuyng, whiche is the lande promiſed to the iuſt. In many other pointes the laws of Moy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes was a ſhadowe of chriſtiani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, but moſte eſpecially in the kynd &amp; maner of gouernement, is liuely repreſented the gouern<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ment vſed in Chriſtes churche: whiche is the matter I ſpecially purpoſe to ſet furth vnto you, &amp; therfore deſire you to geue good eare vnto it. The co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>men weale of the Iewes, in that their paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſage from Egypt to the lande of promiſe, hadde twoo milers, by Gods own appointme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t ſet ouer
<pb facs="tcp:12799:7"/>them, Moyſes and Aaron both preiſtes: but the one, that is Moyſes, which was the higher, made preiſt immediatly by God, the other, that is Aaron, made preiſt at Goddes commaunde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment by Moyſes. Of thoſe two rulers, the higher and worthier receiued at Gods hande all that God woulde haue ſayed to the people, and he deliuered it to Aa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ron, and then Aaron deliuered if to the people, or at the leaſt in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructed the people therin. Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trariwiſe whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the people would haue any queſtion demaunded of God, Aaron did moue that queſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to Moyſes, and Moyſes to God: So that Moyſes was Aaro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s mouth, in thinges to be mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued from the people to God: and Aaron was Moyſes mouthe in
<pb facs="tcp:12799:7"/>thinges to be reueled from God to the people: as it is written in the .iiii. of Exodus, where god ſpe<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>keth thus to Moyſes. <hi>Ipſe loque<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur pro te ad populum &amp; erit os tuum. Tu autem eris ei in his quae ad deum pertinent,</hi> that is. Thy brother Aaron ſhalbe thy ſpokeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man to the people, he ſhalbe thy mouthe. And thou ſhalte be hys ſpokeſman, and hys mouthe in thinges that come from GOD. Againe Moyſes went vp to the toppe of mount Sinay, &amp; there talked face to face with GOD: but Aaron in the meane ſeaſon taried beneth at the foote of the hyll emonge the people to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructe and guyde them. Theſe iii. pointes in Moyſes &amp; Aaron, as they were thinges fulfilled in dede in their perſons, ſo were
<pb facs="tcp:12799:8"/>they ſignifications of thynges to come, in the ſtate of chriſtia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitie. For as S. Paule ſaieth in the firſt to the Corinthyans the te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>th chapitre. <hi>Haec omnia in figura contingebant illis,</hi> All theſe thin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges chaunced to the Iewes in a type or figure. And in the tenthe to the Hebreues heal ſoo ſaieth, <hi>Vmbram habens lex futuroru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> non ipſa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> imaginem reru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.</hi> The lawe of Moyſes hadde but a ſhadowe of thinges to come, &amp; not the true ſhape of thoſe thinges in dede. To come therfore to the publike weale of Chriſtendome, and the gouernement therof: There are in the churche of Chriſt alwayes two head rulers, bothe preiſtes, that is, Chriſt oure hyghe preiſt made by God the father immedi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>atlye, accordinge as we reed in
<pb facs="tcp:12799:8"/>the hundreth and ninth pſalme, <hi>Tu es ſacer dos ineternum ſecundu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ordinem Melchiſedech.</hi> The other preiſt inferior to Chriſt, and yet gouernour of the whole church, firſt was ſaint Peter, and now is his ſucceſſor. Now Peter was made preiſt by Chriſt, as Aaron was by Moyſes; and his ſucceſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſours are made preiſtes by men as Aarons ſucceſſours were. Chriſte is Peters ſpokeſman to God, and Peter was Chriſtes mouthe to the church as appea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth in the .xxii. of Luke, in theſe wordes, <hi>Simon, Simon, ecce Satha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nas experiuit uos, ur cribraret, ſicut triticum, Ego autem rogaui pro te ur non deficiat fides tua. Tu autem aliquando conuerſus, confirma fra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tres tuos.</hi> Simon, Simon, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold Sathan hathe deſired you
<pb facs="tcp:12799:9"/>to ſifte you as it were wheate: but I have prayed for the, that thy faieth faile not: &amp; when thou ſhalt be conuerted, confirme thy brethren. In that Chriſte prai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth for Peter to God the father, that Peters faieth ſhoulde not faile, he is Peters mouth to god ward, as Moyſes was Aaro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s. Agayne in that Peter confir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth his brethren, in the trueth of chriſtes religion, he is chriſtes mouthe to the people. Chriſt is aſcended in to the highe mount of heauen, <hi>Vt appareat nunc vul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tui dei pro nobis.</hi> That he might appeare before the face of God for vs. But the other ruler that is chriſtes vicar, remaineth here on earth, to gouerne the churche militaunt, as did Aaron emong the Iſraelites, as ſhall anone
<pb facs="tcp:12799:9"/>appere mooſte euidently by ine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uitable authorities of the new teſtame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t. Now when God had placed thoſe two prieſtes in the gouernment of the Iewes, hee would ſuch obedience to be giue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vnto, them of the whole people, that none might once repine a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſte the authoritie of either of them, as is euide<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t in the .xvi. of Numbres, where Chore, Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>than, and Abiron, for making rebellion againſt Moiſes, and Aaron, were ſwalowed vp in to the earth aliue, and moſt terri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly periſhed, that the reſt myght by their example, feare at any time to attempt the like. And in the .xvii. of Numbres, GOD to declare, that hee had appointed Aaron as wel as Moiſes, to be rular ouer the Iſraelites, cauſed
<pb facs="tcp:12799:10"/>euery captain of the twelue tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bes to bring in a rodde to Moy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, and al the twelue roddes to bee layed in the tabernacle all night, and whoſe rodde ſhoulde burgin on the morowe, that he was the chefe gouernour vnder Moyſes. Which being done, on the morow, Aarons rodde was founde with buddes on it. The ſame authoritie that was in Aaro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> at that time, and thus co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmed miraculouſly, remained in the high prieſt, Aarons ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſour from tyme to tyme ſo long as the eſtate of that co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mon weith endured. Euen ſo is it ut Chriſtendome. Peter fyrſt was placed in the chief gouernement vnder Chriſt, and after Peter his ſucceſſours continue in the ſame, and haue the rule of the
<pb facs="tcp:12799:10"/>whole church. But you wil per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>adue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ture require farther proofe hereof, and woulde gladly here whether this may be eſtabliſhed by the ghoſpel, and the auncient fathers: wherin for your conte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ta<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> I will ſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>what ſay. And fyrſt touching Peter and his autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie wee reade in the .xvii. of Mathew, how the gatherers of the tribute money came to aſke the tribute of Chriſt, and how Chriſt bade Peter caſt hys angle into the ſee, &amp; looke what fiſhe he tooke firſt, he tolde him that in his mouth he ſhould find ſo much money as two me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> were bound to pay and ſaid, <hi>da eis pro me et te.</hi> Paye that money to the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> for me and thy ſelfe. Vpon this facte of Chriſte S. Auguſtine ſaith <hi>Didrachma capitum ſolutio
<pb facs="tcp:12799:11"/>intelligitur. Saluator cum pro ſe et Petro dari iubet, pro omnibus exol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiſſe videtur: quod ſicut in ſalua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tore erant omnes cauſa magiſterii, ita et poſt ſaluatore<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in Petro omnes continentur: ipſum enim conſtitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>it caput eoru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>:</hi> that is to ſay, The tribute money was hed money or paiment which euery hed or ruler was bound to pay. Wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore when our ſauiour co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded the tribute to be paied for himſelf and for Peter, he ſemeth to haue paied for them all. For as they were all in our ſauiour by reaſon he was their maiſter, ſo after our ſauiour they were all conteined in Peter. For he had made Peter their hed or ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ler. The ſame S. Auſtine wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that place of S. Luke in his .xxii. chapter where Chriſt
<pb facs="tcp:12799:11"/>ſaieth that he praied for Peter, hath theſe wordes, <hi>Non orauit pro Iacobo et Ioanne et reliquis, ſed pro Petro in quo reliqui con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinentur,</hi> Chriſte did not pray for Iames and Iohn and for the reſt of his Apoſtles, but for Peter, in whome the reſt are co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained. In the .xxi. of Mathew we finde how our ſauiour ſayed vnto Peter in moſt ſpeciall and earneſt maner, <hi>paſce agnos, paſce agnos, paſce oues,</hi> fede my lambes fede my lambes, fede my ſhepe: And though certe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of the other a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles, &amp; thei alſo the moſt nota bleſt, were then preſent, Yet he gaue the charge onely to Peter. Wherupo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Cipria<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, Chriſoſtome, Ambroſe, Auſtine, gather that Peter was made rular aboue &amp; ouer them all. Now as concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning
<pb facs="tcp:12799:12"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb facs="tcp:12799:12"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb facs="tcp:12799:13"/>Peters ſucceſſours, where they are to be found and of their authoritie writeth the auncie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t father <hi>Ireneus,</hi> in his third boke againſt y<hi rend="sup">e</hi>; hereſies of <hi>Valentinus,</hi> and other heretikes, and in the thirde chapiter of the ſame boke in this maner. <hi>Quoniam valde longum eſt omnium eccleſiarum enumerare ſucceſſiones, maximae et antiquiſſemae et o<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>nibus cognitae a glorioſiſſimis duobus Apoſtolis Petro et paulo Romae fundatae et conſtitutae eccleſiae, eam qua<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> habet ab apoſtolis traditione<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> et annu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ciata<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> hominibus fidem per ſucceſſiones epiſcoporu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> peruenie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tem vſque ad nos, indicantes confundimus eos omnes qui quoquo modo vel per ſui complacentiam malam, velva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nam gloriam, vel per caecitatem et mala<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſententia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, preterquàm opor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tet
<pb facs="tcp:12799:13"/>colligunt. Ad ha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>c enim eccleſia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> propter potentiorem principali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tatem neceſſe eſt omnem co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>uenire eccleſiam, hoc eſt eos qui ſu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t vndi<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> fideles,</hi> that is to ſay. Foraſmuch as it were a long proceſſe to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cite the ſucceſſion of all chriſten ſeas, we ſhowe the ſucceſſion of Biſhoppes in the greateſt, the moſt aunciente, and the moſte knowen ſea, founded and ſtabli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed at Rome by the moſt gloria apoſtles Petre &amp; Paule: and we declare what is the tradicion, which that ſea hath receiued fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the apoſtles and what faith hath ben preached to men there, and is comen by ſucceſſion of by<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſhoppes euen vnto vs, and ſo do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing we confound and put to ſy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence al thoſe, which by any mea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nes either by ſtanding to muche
<pb facs="tcp:12799:14"/>in their own co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ceite, or for vaine glorye, or through blinde igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raunce, or throughe wrong opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion, dooe gather otherwiſe in matters of religion then is be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>houable. For vnto this ſea, by reſon of the higher gouernment, euery ſea, that is, all faithful, wherſoeuer they dwel, muſt ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des haue recourſe. The like is alſo in Sainct Auſtine in hys, cxlv. epiſtle, where he improuing the ſecte of the Donatiſtes wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth in this maner, <hi>Si ordo epiſco poru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſibi ſucce dentium co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſideran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dus eſt, qua<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>to citius et vere ſalubri ter ab ipſo Petro numeramus, cui totius eccleſiae figuram gerenti do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minus ait. Tu es Petrus, et ſuper hanc Petra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> aedificabo eccleſia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>,</hi> If the order of Biſhops ſucce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding one a nother is to be conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered,
<pb facs="tcp:12799:14"/>howe much more ſoner &amp; in dede more wholſomly doe we recken from Peter himſelf, vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to whom bearing the figure of the whole church, our lord ſaith: Thou art Peter, and vpon this rocke will I builde my churche: And within a litle after he ſaith <hi>In hoc ordine ſucceſſionis nullus Donatiſta inuenitur.</hi> In this or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der of ſucceſſion no Donatiſt is founde. Thus concerning the primacye of S. Peter and hys ſucceſſours, we haue matter ſuf<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ficient both in ſcripture and in the fathers to content vs. But it may not here be omitted, that though in the numbre of many ſucceſſours of Sainct Peter it might ſomtime chau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce ſome one or mo to be euil: yet that nothig can preiudicate to the authorite
<pb facs="tcp:12799:15"/>nor me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ought therfore to with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>draw their obedience. And that in this point alſo ye may ſe good mater to content you: I ſhal re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cite a notable ſayeng of Sainct Auſtin in his forſaied epiſtle to this effecte, where he writeth in this maner. <hi>In illu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> autem ordine<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> epiſcoporu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> qui ducitur ab ipſo Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tro vſo<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> ad Anaſtaſiu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, qui nu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>c ea<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſedet cathedram, etia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſi quiſquàm traditor per illa tempora ſurrep ſiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſet, nihil praeiudicaret eccleſiae, et innoce<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tibus chriſtianis, quibus du<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s prouidens ait de praepoſitis malis: Quae dicu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t facite, quae aute<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> faciunt nolite facere. Dicunt enim &amp; non faciunt, vt certa ſit ſpes fidelis quae no<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in homine, ſed in deo collocata nunquàm tempeſtate ſacrilegi ſcif matis diſſipetur,</hi> that is to ſaye. Thoughe ſome traitour had by theſe days crept into that order,
<pb facs="tcp:12799:15"/>or numbre of Biſhoppes, which is reckened from Peter vnto Anaſtaſius, which now ſitteth in that ſea, yet were it not pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iudicial to the church, and to the innocent chriſten folke, for who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> our lord prouiding ſaieth. Doe the thinges which they ſay, but that they do, do ye not: for they ſaye and doe not, that the hope of a chriſten man might be ſure, and being ſet not on man, but on god, ſhould neuer be ſhaken with any tempeſt or ſtorme of wicked ſciſme. Nowe that ye haue heard how neceſſarye it is for al chriſtendome to be vnder y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> gouerneme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t of the Apoſtolike ſea, and thereby muſt needes perceiue that the benefite of our reconciliation and reduction to that ſea, is a moſt excellent and exceadyng gret benefit: I think
<pb facs="tcp:12799:16"/>good to note vnto you the circu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances incident with the ſame, wherby the benefit is made the more notable. This moſt ioyful reconciliation came vnto this realme on the firſt feaſtiual day in the whole yeare, by the order of the eccleſiaſticall ſeruice, that is, on ſainct Andrewes day. It came in the feaſt of S. Andrew brother to S. Peter, to whoſe ſea we are reconciled, in the day of ſuch a ſaint as was crucified, as bothe Peter was, the firſte that enioyed this autoritie, and as Chriſte was, whoe gaue the autoritie vnto Peter. It chau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced in the tyme of a parliament, and by the full conſent and glad approbatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of the whole realme, in that parliament repreſented: It came vnto vs by oure owne
<pb facs="tcp:12799:16"/>countrey man the moſt honora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble lorde Legates grace, who neuer ſwarued from that ſea: In the raigne of our ſoueraines kynge Phylip and quene Mary, who alwayes continued in their obedyence to that ſupremicye. It came by ſee vnto vs, a mete paſſage for the authoritye of hym, whiche was called to that autoritie frome the ſee, and in his feaſt, who was made an a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle from the ſee, that is of a fyſſher. I ſhall not nede muche to ſpeake of the great euils that this realme is ryd from by this benefit. Euery ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> feleth in him ſelf the great relife, that he hath by his reconciliation: I meane not onely for the temporall cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>elte, myſerye, tumult, feare, and tyrannye, whiche ceaſſe by this
<pb facs="tcp:12799:17"/>benefyte, but moſt of all for the inwarde ghoſtly relyfe, of which ſaincte Paule ſpeakynge in the ſeconde chapiter of his firſt epi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle to the Corinthians, ſayeth: <hi>Quisſcit hominu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> quae ſu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t hominis, niſi ſpiritus hominis qui ipſo eſt? Ita et quae dei ſunt nemo nouit niſi ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritus dei,</hi> what man knoweth the thinges whiche are in man, but the ſpirite of manne whiche is within him? Euen ſo thoſe thin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges whiche longe to god, none knoweth but onely the ſpirite of god. In whiche wordes ſaincte Paule geueth vs to wete, that who ſo hath not y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſpirite of god in him, knoweth not gods truth. Now the ſpirite of god can not be but in them that are of the body, whiche is gouerned with goddes ſpirite, and this bodye is
<pb facs="tcp:12799:17"/>the Churche: whereof they are not, whiche deuyde theim ſelues from the gouernment appointed by god to be in the churche, whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che gouernment is as you haue hearde, the obedience to the ſea of Rome, from whiche we haue deuided our ſelues of late yeres: and wher vnto we were by thys dayes benefit vnited and recon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciled againe. We were I ſay rid from that myſery, which ſainct Paule ſpeaketh of in the ſecond chapiter of his Epiſtle to the E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pheſians, ſayinge: <hi>Eratis illo in tempore ſine chriſto, alienatia con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſatione Iſrael, et hoſpites teſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tamentorum, promiſſionis ſpem non habentes, et ſine deo in hoc mundo.</hi> Ye were at that tyme without Chriſte: Ye were ſtrai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>inge from the conuerſacion of
<pb facs="tcp:12799:18"/>Iſrael, ye were ſtrangers from the teſtamentes hauyng no hope of the promyſſe, and men with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out god in this worlde. Yf wee nowe perceaue theſe two poin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes whiche I haue declared, the one of goddes ſingular benefyte as this day conferred and beſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wed vpon vs, the other touching the dredfull daungers we were in before, we haue then a thirde parte to playe with kynge Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uyd, that is, to acknoweledge theſe miſeries to haue comen vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon vs for oure offences in ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>inge euery one of vs. <hi>Caſtigans caſtigauit me dominus, et morti non tradidit me.</hi> God hath chaſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned me, but he hath not delyue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red me into death. The fourthe poynt alſo is to be ioyned to the other three, that is to giue than<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kes
<pb facs="tcp:12799:18"/>as Dauid dyd, and to exhort all other to do the ſame, whithe for my parte I ſhall do with the wordes of my theme, ſayinge unto you. <hi>Conſtituite diem ſolen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nem in condenſis vſ<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> ad cornu alta<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ris.</hi> Of late men pulled downe aultars, contempned the ſeruice and ſacrifice of the aultar, but now we muſt come in gret mul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titudes to the aultar, to the ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uice of the aultar, and the ſacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice of the aultar, I meane to the Maſſe. And in conſideration of the highe worke of god done on the aultar, we muſt make great ſolempnity, ſpecially on this day And beholde beſides the benefyt of our reconciliacion chauncyng on this daye, we haue yet by S. Andrewe a confirmacion of our beliefe in the ſacrament and ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifice
<pb facs="tcp:12799:19"/>of the aulter by that hee ſaide and did this daye. For a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monge other aunſweres whiche the bleſſed apoſtle S. Andrewe made to the cruel <hi>Aegeas, he ſaid: Omnipote<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ti deo qui vnus &amp; verꝰ eſt, ego omni die ſacrifico. Non thurisfumu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> nec taurorum mugi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>entium carnes, nec hircorum ſan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guine<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, ſed immaculatum agnum quotidle in altari ſacrifico cuius car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes poſteaquàm omnis populꝰ ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ducauerit, &amp; ſanguine<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> eius biberit, tamen integer parmanet &amp; imma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culatus,</hi> that is. I do offer ſacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice euery day to God almighty, not the ſmoke of franckencens, nor the fleſhe of roring bulles or the blood of goates, but I ſacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice euery daye on the aultar the immaculate lambe, whoſe fleſh after that al the people hath ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten
<pb facs="tcp:12799:19"/>and hath dronke his bloud, yet he abideth whole and imma<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>culate. What can bee plainer ſpoken either of the preſence of Chriſtes body &amp; bloud in the ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crament of the aultar, or of the ſacrifice of the Maſſe, then here is ſpoken? And as plainely the ſame bleſſed apoſtle vttereth in that that foloweth, a nother point worthy to be conſidered. For when Aegeas maruailinge at his talke ſaied vnto him: <hi>Quomodo poteſt hoc fieri:</hi> howe can this bee done? S. Andrewe aunſwered. <hi>Sivis ſcire quomodo poteſt fieri, aſſume forma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> diſcipuli vt poſſis diſcernere quod quaeris,</hi> It thou wilt know how it may be done, take vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> thee the ſhape or fourme of a diſciple or lerner, that thou may diſcerne y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> thing
<pb facs="tcp:12799:20"/>that thou aſkeſt. Which becauſe Aegeas would not do, he could not vnderſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d the miſtery, as in our days, ſo many as would pre ſupteouſly teache themſelfes, &amp; not lerne of Chriſtes church, er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red in the truthe of Chriſtes ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>craumentes. Wherfore I ethorte you with the woordes of my theme: kepe this day a ſolemne day: kepe ſolempne proceſſion, make great ſole<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>nitie, ſo as your deuotion may ſtretch euen to the aultar: or rather the prophete Dauid foreſeyng in ſpirite the benefite of chriſtian vnitie, doth exhort you therto, and with the prophete Dauid, S. Peter the prince of the Apoſtles (to whoſe authoritie wee are recouered) ex<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>horteth you, and with Dauid &amp; S. Peter, Peters brother ſaint
<pb facs="tcp:12799:20"/>Andrewe, whoſe feaſt we kepe, exhorteth you: and with the, &amp; aboue them, Chriſt our ſauiour exhorteth you, to reioyce and be thankeful for the great benefite of god comen this day vnto you, that we keping our ſelues with in his folde on earth, maye bee found in the numbre of thoſe la<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bes, which ſra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ding on his right hand at the daye of Dome ſhall heare our lorde ſay vnto them. Come ye bleſſed children of my father poſſeſſe the kyngdome which was prepared for you fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the beginning of the worlde. Which ſend vnto vs al, the father, the ſonne, and the holy ghoſt, to whome be al honour &amp; glo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ry world with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out ende.</p>
            <closer>Amen,</closer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="colophon">
            <pb facs="tcp:12799:21"/>
            <p>Imprynted at London, by Robert Ca<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly, within the precinct of the late deſſolued houſe of the graye Freers, nowe conuerted to an Hoſpitall, called Chriſtes Hoſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tall.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:12799:21"/>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
